<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_basic.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="anc.02119"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc> 
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Introduction to <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi></title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>  
                <author>Eric Conrad</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ec">Eric Conrad</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="smb">Stephanie Blalock</persName> 
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2017</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text encoding and text of this introduction were created and/or prepared by 
                     the <title level="m">Walt Whitman Archive</title> and Eric Conrad, and
                        are licensed under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 
                        International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0). Any reuse of these materials should credit the <title level="m">Walt 
                        Whitman Archive</title> and Eric Conrad.</p>
                </availability>
                <idno>anc.02119</idno> 
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a">Introduction to <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi></title>
                    <note type="project">Written for the <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Archive</hi>. First published on the <hi rend="italic">Archive</hi> in 2017.</note></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2023-04-03" who="#km">updated schema and namespace declarations; other validation updates</change>
            <change when="2017-10-26" who="#smb">corrections</change>
            <change when="2016-08-09" who="#smb">adjusted encoding, renamed file</change>
            <change when="2016-07-01" who="#ec">Encoded</change>
            <change when="2016-06-28" who="#ec">Created as Word-format document</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text type="apparatus"> 
        <body>
            <head type="main-authorial">Introduction to <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi></head>
            <div1 type="section">
                
                <p> When the young Boston publishers Thayer &#38; Eldridge first contacted Walt
                    Whitman in 1860 and pledged to put his book "into good form, and style
                    attractive to the eye," they were aggressively professing their faith that a
                    third edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> could become a major
                    commercial and cultural success. Nowhere is that blind optimism more apparent
                    than in <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi>, an elaborate, 64-page
                    promotional pamphlet Whitman and his publishers created to advertise the third
                    edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> and to capitalize on the
                    growing celebrity of its author. Circulated freely through the mail, <hi
                    rend="italic">Imprints</hi> billed itself as a brochure for "all persons disposed 
                    to commence the study" of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>. Behind its significant 
                    typographical excesses and rhetorical contradictions, <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> strives to 
                    function as a sort of primer on Whitman’s poetic project and on the political, spiritual, and cultural 
                    import of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>.</p>
                 
                <p>Examined within the chaotic context of nineteenth-century advertising, the length
                    and complexity of <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> alone make it an anomaly, but
                    when compared to the restrained promotional practices of other literary
                    publishers, Whitman’s pamphlet stands out in stark contrast as a unique text
                    worthy of careful consideration. While <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> did not,
                    in its time, come to define this moment of American literary promotion,
                    retrospectively it invites us to consider the methods available for nineteenth-century poets 
                    and publishers to distinguish their literary commodities and authorial personas in rapidly expanding and 
                    increasingly unpredictable markets. In theory, the success of <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> as a 
                    promotional device hinges on its reader’s willingness to "study" Whitman and his poetry. By flouting emerging 
                    advertising conventions that called for clarity, simplicity, and brevity, the odd assortment of material 
                    found in <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> breaks every law of modern advertising: it demands more than mere 
                    passive consumption. The cramped pamphlet contains twenty-six individual entries, most of which are previously 
                    published reviews of the first and second edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi>, ranging from some of the 
                    harshest critiques ever levied against Whitman to overwhelmingly positive puffs, including some the poet 
                    published anonymously about himself. Mixed in with these reviews are a number of pieces&#8212;including 
                    two stories debating Whitman’s rumored stint as an omnibus driver&#8212;that focus exclusively on Whitman 
                    as a personality rather than his literary work. What we are left with is an incredibly complex and 
                    contradictory piece of advertising ephemera, a dense promotional pamphlet that sells Whitman and his 
                    poetry by giving readers seemingly indiscriminate access to the positive, negative, and, at times, 
                    sensational coverage the poet and <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> received in the American and British press.</p>
                
                <p>This curious and compact volume, what Whitman once called "the little book before
                    the war," had a relatively large circulation, thanks in part to Thayer &#38; Eldridge’s penchant for 
                    unorthodox marketing techniques. Most print advertisements for the 1860 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> 
                    mention <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> by name, 
                    offering to mail the pamphlet to readers simply for the price of postage. As these traditional advertisements
                    were appearing in a variety of periodicals across the country, Thayer &#38;
                    Eldridge also ran&#8212;without Whitman’s consent&#8212;a cryptic notice in <hi rend="italic">Frank Leslie’s 
                    Illustrated Newspaper</hi> that neither mentions the poet nor his publishers by name. 
                    This unassuming advertisement published under the enticing title "A Good Book Free" 
                    enacted Thayer 	&#38; Eldridge’s plan to give <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> a "very wide 
                    and telling circulation" by promising to mail "One of the most interesting and spicy Books 
                    ever published," packed with "64 pages of excellent reading matter." Assuring readers it 
                    was "no advertisement of a patent medicine or other humbug"&#8212;a guarantee that should 
                    indicate just how outlandish Thayer &#38; Eldridge’s scheme was&#8212;the notice vowed to 
                    deliver "a handsome and well-printed book" which would both “amuse and instruct” audiences. Of 
                    course, that "handsome book" was not Whitman’s poetry, but <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi>. In the 
                    wake of the <hi rend="italic">Frank Leslie</hi>’s campaign, Whitman’s publishers received hundreds of requests a day
                    for <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi>, though the pamphlet’s actual impact on sales is difficult to determine precisely.</p>
                
                <p>Whitman’s shifting attitudes toward the design and circulation of <hi
                    rend="italic">Imprints</hi> are as contradictory as the contents of the pamphlet
                    itself. Lingering concerns over Thayer &#38; Eldridge’s overzealous handling of
                    <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> might, in part, explain Whitman’s protest later
                    in life to Horace Traubel that the pamphlet was “not my book,” insisting to his
                    friend that he had "nothing to do with it." During a different conversation with
                    Traubel, however, Whitman took sole credit for <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi>'
                    design, calling it a "sort of barricade" he "set . . . up" to hold back the
                    "desperate assaults" of his enemies. "When most everybody lied about me,"
                    Whitman explained on this occasion, <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> gave him an
                    opportunity "to tell the truth about myself." Considering the odd assortment of
                    material found in <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> (especially the inclusion of
                    vicious attacks on <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>), neither of Whitman’s
                    characterizations&#8212;that he either had no part in the conception of Imprints
                    or that he was the chief engineer behind it&#8212;seems entirely plausible. Yet,
                    <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> falls neatly into Whitman’s evolving promotional
                    strategies for the three antebellum editions of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of
                        Grass</hi>.  As early as 1855, the poet was including reviews printed from
                    carefully worked-over proofs alongside his poetry, binding this material into later issues of
                    the first edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> in a way that
                    clearly anticipated the pre-planned "Leaves-Dropping" annex of the 
                    1856 edition. <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi> takes this earlier 
                    strategy a step further, adopting an even more expansive approach to literary 
                    advertising, creating a separately circulated pamphlet out of the same type of 
                    material Whitman had been positioning alongside his poetry since the 
                    inception of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>.</p>
                
                <p>One of the most difficult challenges Whitman and his publishers faced in <hi
                    rend="italic">Imprints</hi> was to mobilize criticism of two earlier (and quite
                    different) editions of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> to sell the new,
                    "complete" 1860 volume. In their attempt to distance the Thayer &#38; Eldridge
                    edition from its "temporary and partial" predecessors, Whitman and his
                    publishers continually emphasize the "superb" quality of the new electrotype
                    edition. The contents of <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> attest to the fierce
                    critical debate over the value of Whitman’s poetry in 1860, but the pamphlet’s
                    typographical eccentricities allude to a fact that few of even Whitman’s most 
                    passionate detractors would dispute: Thayer &#38; Eldridge’s edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> was 
                    a singular, if not beautiful, printed object.  George Searle Philips, one of Whitman’s early champions 
                    whose "Letter Impromptu" appears in <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi>, described the third edition 
                    as "perhaps, the most magnificent specimen of typography ever issued by the American Press." It was 
                    the <hi rend="italic">Westminster Review</hi>, though, that drew the starkest contrast between 
                    the elegance of Thayer &#38; Eldridge’s book and the perversity of Whitman’s verse, 
                    marveling at how poetry containing such "obscenity and profanity" could appear 
                    amidst "all the glories of hot-pressed paper, costly binding, and stereotype printing."</p>
                
                <p>As an advertisement for America’s "most magnificent specimen of typography," <hi
                    rend="italic">Imprints</hi> goes to lengths to display the variety of typefaces
                    and ornamentation that readers could find in Thayer &#38; Eldridge’s volume.
                    Whitman had direct control over the distinctive visual aspects of the 1860 
                    <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, precisely the features 
                    <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi>’ layout accentuates. Taking full advantage
                    of the autonomy his publishers granted him, Whitman hand-picked fonts and
                    flourishes for the 1860 edition from several books, most importantly 
                    <hi rend="italic">Specimens of Printing Types, Plain and Ornamental, Borders,
                     Cuts, Rules, Dashes Etc. from the Factory of L. Johnson &#38; Co.</hi>
                    (Philadelphia, 1859). From Johnson’s massive collection, Whitman selected a
                    dozen or so fonts for <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi>, most of which are also
                    jammed into <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> where a single page may contain up to six 
                    different typefaces. This frenzied typographical display was meant to give readers a 
                    sense of the "superior manner" in which Thayer &#38; Eldridge’s edition was printed. 
                    The back of the pamphlet promises that the typography of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi> "will be found to vie 
                    in elegance with any thing ever issued from the American or English press." By sampling different 
                    typefaces&#8212;and by prominently reprinting an illustration central to the 1860 edition, 
                    a manicule (or little hand) with a butterfly perched on it&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> 
                    gives readers a visual approximation of what they would find within Thayer &#38; Eldridge’s "ELEGANT BOOK," enticing 
                    consumers with glimpses of what Whitman had in-store for them in his larger volume.</p>
                
                <p>While the primary purpose of <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> was to sell copies
                    of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>, the pamphlet is equally concerned
                    with establishing and promoting Whitman’s own celebrity imprint.  The pun
                    evident in "Leaves-Droppings," the annex to the 1856 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of
                    Grass</hi>, suggests to the reader that he or she is listening in on a private 
                    conversation between Ralph Waldo Emerson and Whitman, whose letters to one another 
                    are included in the edition’s paratextual appendix.  More so, "Leaves-Droppings" would have readers believe 
                    they are eavesdropping on the beginning of a national conversation, a discussion displaying Whitman’s 
                    growing cultural relevance. <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi> intensifies the punning 
                    of "Droppings." Within the pamphlet, Whitman demonstrates the marks he has made on America through 
                    his own writing, itself a type of imprint. The pamphlet moves beyond the tentative "listening-in" quality 
                    of "Droppings" and makes a stronger declaration of Whitman’s enduring and recognizable contributions. By 1860 you no longer had to 
                    strain your ear to hear Whitman’s name; you could now easily see the imprint of his poetry 
                    everywhere. <hi rend="italic">Imprints</hi> offers itself as evidence that Whitman was beginning 
                    to achieve at least part of the "proof of a poet" he first articulated in the 1855 preface: his country was absorbing 
                    him, even if not yet as "affectionately as he [had] absorbed it."</p>
               
            </div1>
                
            <div1 type="bibliography">
                
                <head type="main-authorial">Bibliography</head>
                
                <listBibl>
                    
                    <bibl>Blake, David Haven. <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman and the Culture of
                        American Celebrity</hi>. New Haven: 
                        Yale University Press, 2006.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Conrad, Eric. "The Walt Whitman Brand: <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> and Literary Promotion, 1855&#8211;1892.” 
                        Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Iowa, 2013.
                    </bibl> 
                    <bibl>Folsom, Ed. "Appearing in Print: Illustrations of the Self in <hi
                        rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>," <hi rend="italic">The 
                        Cambridge Companion to Walt Whitman</hi>, edited by Ezra Greenspan (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1995), 135&#8211;165.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Folsom, Ed. <hi rend="italic">Whitman Making Books / Books Making Whitman</hi>. Iowa City: Obermann Center for 
                        Advanced Studies, 2005.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Gailey, Amanda. "Walt Whitman and the King of Bohemia: The Poet in the <hi rend="italic">Saturday 
                        Press</hi>." <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman Quarterly Review</hi> (Spring
                        2008): 143&#8211;166.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Genoways, Ted. <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman and the Civil War: America’s Poet during the Lost Years of 
                        1860&#8211;1862</hi>. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2009.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Greenspan, Ezra. <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman and the American Reader</hi>. New York: Cambridge 
                        University Press, 1990.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Morton, Heather. "Democracy, Self-Reviews and the 1855 <hi
                        rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi>." <hi rend="italic">Virginia 
                        Quarterly Review</hi> (Spring 2005): 229&#8211;243. 
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>O’Driscoll, Michael J. "Whitman in the Archive: <hi rend="italic">Leaves
                        of Grass</hi> and the Culture of the 
                        Book." <hi rend="italic">English Studies in Canada</hi> 25(1999): 295&#8211;323.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Reynolds, David S. <hi rend="italic">Walt Whitman’s America</hi>. New York: Vintage Books, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Traubel, Horace. <hi rend="italic">With Walt Whitman in Camden</hi>. Various publishers, 1906&#8211;1996.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Whitley, Edward. "Presenting Walt Whitman: 'Leaves-Droppings' as Paratext." <hi rend="italic">Walt 
                        Whitman Quarterly Review</hi> (Summer 2001): 1&#8211;17.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>Whitt, Jan, "<hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass Imprints</hi> (1860)," <hi
                        rend="italic">Walt Whitman: An Encyclopedia</hi>, edited 
                        by J. R. LeMaster and Donald D. Kummings (New York: Garland, 1998), 381.
                    </bibl>
                  
                </listBibl>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>